welcome to moomoomath and science in the
carbon cycle
carbon is an element that is vital to
most living organisms on earth
it is also a key component of our
atmosphere
carbon has the ability to cycle through
our earth the ocean
living factors abiotic factors in the
air
the carbon recycles among five major
locations
these items include the atmosphere
the terrestrial biosphere or land
the earth's interior the ocean
and human influence let's take a look at
what happens at each of these areas
carbon is found in the atmosphere in at
least two forms carbon dioxide and
methane
this atmospheric carbon can be absorbed
by autotrophs like plants and plankton
to be used for photosynthesis it can
also be absorbed by bodies of water
and the ocean when carbon is absorbed by
the ocean it reacts with the water and
creates carbonic acid
the terrestrial biosphere which is
another term for the earth's land
has several paths of carbon that it can
take
first there is an exchange between
plants and animals
plants absorb carbon in the form of
carbon dioxide for photosynthesis
and animals release carbon dioxide
during cellular respiration
also heterotrophs eat plants that
contain carbon
animals also release carbon as methane
during digestion
and the soil contains decomposers that
release carbon into the atmosphere and
the soil
carbon is also stored in the earth's
interior
carbon in the lithosphere includes
fossil fuels like coal
oil and natural gas along with deposits
like limestone
and volcanoes may release some of this
carbon stored
in the lithosphere when they erupt
up next the ocean the ocean has the
greatest
exchange quantity of cycled carbon and
stores a large amount of carbon
the ocean absorbs carbon in the form of
carbon dioxide
the ocean also has a large amount of
plankton
that absorbs carbon dioxide that it uses
for photosynthesis
humans also influence the movement of
carbon
humans burn fossil fuel which releases
carbon dioxide into the atmosphere
also the production of clinker which is
used for cement from limestone
also releases carbon in addition
deforestation from humans can cause
the amount of carbon in the atmosphere
to increase
so there you go an overview of the path
of an atom of carbon
that may take place during the carbon
cycle
thanks for watching and moon math
uploads a new map
and science video every day please
subscribe and
share